so that was so exquisite and brilliant
and important and critical and there's
about a million things I'd like to say
about it all great and so I actually
have notes on what I want to make sure I
say just in this comment because because
it's important and rather than add
anything I just want to acknowledge a
few things and the first one is as sure
as I am that we have this fork in the
road rather this unique time that we're
not gonna make it through if we don't
change our relationship to ecosystem the
biosphere to be a healthy adaptive
integrated one as sure as I am of that
I'm also sure we're not going to make it
through if we don't change our
relationship to sexuality and pleasure
and relationship and eros in exactly the
kinds of ways you're talking about so
it's that important and I think the two
topics are totally related and we've
been telling this universe story here
together and it's a new universe story
and we're wanting to tell one that's
congruent and that makes sense and it
gives us a vision of the future and
shows us our place in it and it reclaims
meaning and aliveness in a really deep
way and the part that you just shared
that you just added to everything we've
done so far really is the inside of the
inside of the story really is in the
heart of the story where the deepest
part of meaning and aliveness comes and
it's just there's just so much pleasure
for me arising listening to it and and
the thing that I really appreciate the
most and what you just shared and then
everything that you share is that the
unique self kind of insight as you share
it can seem at first like it's a mostly
human teaching that is really important
and critical at the human level and
that's just one expression of what's
really a lens for a comprehensive
ontology at the University and so
getting that there's a uniqueness to
every emotion to every human attribute
every quality that has something to
offer universe that none of the other
ones do where the whole universe is
missing without it and that leads to
this great reclaiming that is like the
essence of what I see you teaching and
doing reclaiming
sexuality reclaiming
pleasure reclaiming eros even reclaiming
judgment it's almost like every
everything that has a shadow side where
the shadows had had been so painful that
it was right for us to throw them out
until we knew how to do it better and
yet the light side of it the whole
universe is missing without it
obligation and so how to bring all of
that together and synthesize it like
awesome awesome awesome thank you damn
it fantastic fantastic Jessica no thank
you for um for sharing something that I
feel is seminal to or transition awesome
know that the source code of pleasures
so exciting and I'm just delighted to
get the reflection and to have this
conversation with you and work will
evolve this together you don't I put an
obligation on that list also yeah I just
you know that's it will reclaim these
course structures you know is the next
contract move yeah principle of non
rejection well what's what's so
interesting to me that I didn't really
understand fully until I heard you speak
is the degree of pleasure that I receive
from being part of the evolutionary
impulse and that's like a jump between
the maybe and leaving out a few but how
in the world did I jump to to feeling
that and experiencing the ecstatic
reality of the force of creation
incarnate right so I would like to just
say that maybe the all the levels of
pleasure and if this is the sixth I'm
not sure what search level it is that
this level six should include all of
them that's right and I can see that if
you only emphasize any one of them it's
not enough but emphasizing six because I
think six is what's needed in this
decade of life because if we don't go to
the social jump race like Daniel is
saying if we don't go to that design
process and if we bring all the pleasure
into it and see this as ultimate
pleasure yeah that I have felt but I
need to get all the other levels so that
everybody
and get them along with me including
myself yeah my self so it's really
really helpful to merge with Daniel and
me both of us having jumped into the
design revolution right
I mean to jump into the impulsive
creation in body and characterizing
society than to get all these other
levels of pleasure then we have a
movement transform humanity because it
will all be there no no that's that's
fantastic Barbara and fantastic Daniel
let's just play for a second so in the
principles of pleasure so one principle
we saw was that if you remove one of the
levels then you get less pleasure from
the other ones
that's one principle right so we looked
at kind of for example physical pleasure
you know relational pleasure and meaning
pleasure and we just saw that you're on
vacation in Jamaica you know with a job
I know works a bitch that's one
principle but there's a second principle
which says there's no rate of exchange
between them now let me add another
principle which I like to call pleasure
absolutism you have to beware of
pleasure absolutism and you can actually
interpret history in the universe
historical story as different epochs in
history freeze framing and absolute
izing or different streams of movement a
different particular dimension of
pleasure hmm you know so that um the
classical hedonist of course is you know
picking level two pleasure you know a
level one pleasure excuse me you know
classical you know physical pleasures
you know America has got a huge
obsession with level two pleasure right
you know it's actually know you're
relaxed that's really what it's about
doesn't fully understand level three
pleasure other societies were very
functional productive menial level three
pleasure right enlightenment society is
level four pleasure
and each one has a shadow super Kadam
from Marxism right its shadow was the
shadow of level six pleasure and it's
Marxism understood level six pleasure
but but again when you absolute eyes a
pleasure and you ignore the other levels
so for example you might ignore the
irreducible dignity of the unique self
as you can't kill 17,000,000 collective
farmers right but but what was driving
right the communist impulse was actually
evolutionary pleasure was excess it was
a
an impulse right but when you absolute
eyes it you get destruction so actually
the realization that evolution is
pleasure is critical and was critical to
all three of us and holding all six
right and we all six are valid and they
need to be in relationship to each other
right so one of the principles is
balance that you need balance between
the pleasures and the second pleasure
out of balance right the system kind of
runs amok and so actually the way to
actually chart our own emergence but is
to actually do a check of our pleasures
where am i you can actually do a
pleasure check where am I at all six and
you'll find that any here's the wild
paradox any ethical acting out any
psychological breakdown right any kind
of you know you know kind of something
which is kind of a violation of what you
think your own higher self is you will
always be able to trace back to a lack
in either a depth or quality or
dimension of one of the six levels of
pleasure
so it actually emerges as the opposite
of what we usually think all breakdowns
in ethics are based on failures and eros
and pleasure
mmm-hmm and that's the that's the
ethical principle that I you know I
didn't have time to talk about it in the
but and that's the entire place this is
going is paradoxically and I wrote an
article that decade ago in a cover of
tycoon magazine right it was called on
the erotic and the ethical people just
read the title and they attacked it and
even read the article it was just like
like what's he did right because the
people are so there's the Iraq and
there's the ethical know right and and
the ethical breakdowns always happen
when there's a failure of our awesome
pleasure and that just changes the whole
game
you know I just want to tell a brief
story when I was a citizen diplomat in
the Soviet Union how the Cold War time
well I took a whole troop of people over
there who were paying their own way to
go to give gifts and make friends and so
forth the senator for Soviet American
dialogue and so one day we were talking
to one of their head newscasters and he
said well who's paying you to do this we
said oh we're paying it out of our
retirement funds to come to be with you
what
and it was real shock right and he said
oh my god this is what we thought the
communist men would be right that the
citizens from the united states that
were going over there at their own
expense hmm freely of pleasure right and
when he saw this and real if there was a
downfall in his face because they had
hoped that by getting rid of private
property they would create to the
impulse that the citizens of the US felt
at that time to give their gifts to to
people in the Soviet Union
Wow that's beautiful that's complete
aful thank you this exact great it's
exactly why I say I'm so sure that this
is necessary not just important and
meaningful right necessary to make it as
we've been talking about the need for
emergent self-governance and that
imposed government doesn't work and that
means governing our own life and then
being able to interact in interdependent
ways so functional independence and
functional interdependence at
progressively wide rate levels and so
there's this relationship between
sovereignty and pleasure that's so deep
that and also between Communion and
pleasure right it's both both sides of
it where if you know that as a social
scientist and as an activist coming to
this there's such interesting social
science from the correlation of how
violent a culture is with how sexually
repressed they are right the more sexual
press the more violent and vice versa
because if you want to have a dominator
culture or a few control of many to do
things that are not good to them in you
have to have them not listen to what
actually feels that's right good right
to them and so when you teach kids and
sex is such a big part of it but all
kinds of pleasures when you teach them
that what feels best to them is really
bad so they can't trust their own
feelings they have to defer to an
authority as great an authority
structure that's exactly right and if
you want to have sovereigns that self
lead and then interact with others to be
able to interdependently lead there has
to be a level of self referral self
trust ray or of it don't know that's
that that's exactly right
I mean that's as long as we have a
society in which there's a clash between
our own deepest experiences of pleasure
without an actual
of pleasure right we're never gonna be
able to actually transform consciousness
you can only transform conscience at the
root as long as you don't shift the
source code of pleasure
you're always imposing a map right in a
way that's that's ultimately destructive
it's got to be destructive because
there's this essential internal clash
and happening within the human being
right that's you know that that's
impossible to move beyond and here of
course is the paradox pleasure doesn't
mean less effort right right you know
pleasure planets people understand plus
that's how the principles of pleasure is
so important you made it very clear
right pleasure pleasure pleasure
actually requires full commitment I mean
it's kind of like I mean and take you
know you know and you get to fully show
up when you surrender you know and all
the paradoxes I mean let's take
sexualities for a second what happens in
order for sexual adder to work what
happens you need to be able to let
someone else witness your surrender
right intimacy is when someone else
witnesses your surrender now undo they
witness your surrender
they actually witness yourself
involvement because there's a certain
moment which is kind of the kind of
contemporary kind of feel-good beautiful
sacred sexuality Skip's in genuine
sexuality as a point when you actually
go in work right and you've got to be so
deep in the intimacy that you're willing
to let that person witness you're going
inward actually away from them into
separateness in order to create
communion and it's dancing in that
paradox is where intimacy happens it's
that's where sacred sexuality actually
happens right and in that sense we'll
talk about this you know in one of our
um and one of our you know bonus things
we'll do a section on sexuality but but
of course the sexual models right eros
in every dimension of being I mean last
example what does a person cry out at a
moment of orgasm right cross-cultural
issue right Oh God or in our Elohim or
whatever version and the name the other
person right and we talked about this
once right
oh why saying the name of the other
person in God at the same time strange
thing to say and of course the deepest
revelation is is that you realize in
that moment that Oh God in the name of
the other person are the same there's no
difference right that that person's name
their unique self is God uniquely
expressing them and when you're fully
self involved in that that's some point
open you actually see with God's eyes
and you call it Oh God and name the
other person which is the same sacred
text and it's a sacred text and that's
the Tantra trickster that's kind of
revealing kind of dust and we need to
kind of take this and make it source
code of culture which has obligation
commitment the whole thing it's exciting
it's exciting yeah it's exciting I want
to add to that as Marshall Rosenberg has
this great quote that if you want to be
a peacemaker you have to master conflict
you have to master going into it so that
you can actually heal it and dress it
and that means dealing with the
elephants in the living room that really
mess stuff up if they don't get dealt
with right and in the evolutionary
movement the social design movement
sexuality is such an elephant in the
living room where it's easy okay let's
talk about economics let's talk about
governance let's talk about
infrastructure that wasn't so taboo that
we're just gonna get in trouble if we do
it and then we'll be less credible in
these other areas and yet it's so core
to I mean just getting we all got here
that way right like it's one of the few
things that is in common to to all of us
that's so deeply moving and if we don't
if we don't actually address it we don't
get to fix the other things and it takes
courage to do that and it's critical and
so I'm really happy that you're doing
that and we're together yeah awesome so
great to be together Barbara give us a
concluding blessing well I think that if
we take all the six levels right over to
the level of co-creation right and the
wheel of co-creation in what I'm
understanding is a wheel of intense
pleasure right because I've experienced
it when it works it's when people start
taking down the walls that separate us
in all those sectors and finding how to
co-create with each other
there is an explosion of love and one
day in one of those sin comes astronaut
Edgar Mitchell came in and he saw the
walls coming down and people were
circling around and they were ecstatic
Dadich when the walls came down and
joining together and he said if I had a
spiritual Geiger counter it would have
gone off the charts and we didn't even
mention is this spiritual right the
meaning of
lagares right who bind back and make
whole yeah and I think the reason that
I've been so pleasurably excited about
coming together as a whole if you want
to take that in its sexual super sexual
terminology rape requires all the other
levels of human pleasure to be included
openly and understandingly in order to
get to the thing that we need to do in
this next decade and I am speaking like
a mother giving birth yes it's really
fine a to say we'll wait 25 30 years but
not if you're giving birth right
assuming there's a time factor so it all
the pleasures my concluding statement
would be have to really come in
relatively quickly yeah yeah really nice
assignment it's a nice assignment
Harvard Daniel what a pleasure thank you
very much thank you very much